<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from no far countrey being a judgement upon the present posture of affairs in England &amp;c. : written to, and made publike at the request of a worthy person elected to serve in the approaching parliament, as worth the serious consideration of his fellow members.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1492</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43392</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27378325</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27378325</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110096</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48071)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110096)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1725:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from no far countrey being a judgement upon the present posture of affairs in England &amp;c. : written to, and made publike at the request of a worthy person elected to serve in the approaching parliament, as worth the serious consideration of his fellow members.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Year, 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated on p. 14: April 6th. 1660.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110096:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER From no far COUNTREY, BEING A Judgement upon the preſent poſture of Affairs in ENGLAND, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN TO, And made publike at the requeſt of a Worthy Perſon elected to ſerve in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>As worth the ſerious conſideration of his Fellow Members.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:110096:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110096:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER From no far COUNTREY,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I thank you for your news and the newſ-books you ſent me, which neither of them by any art of mine are to be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with themſelves, for you tell me while a Common-wealth ſeemeth to be declared for, Common-wealthſ-men are as it were kickt out of all imployment, civil or military. Much hath been ſaid heretofore of a threefold cord, but I like not your Stateſmen, that work like Ropers, nor ſee, how a ſlippery trick ſhould be the cauſe of a ſteddy Government. But however your Commonwealthſ-men may do, by your news, their principles by your books, I mean the Votes, and Acts of Parliament, will ſhift well enough for themſelves. It is true that the whip and the bell, the ſcourges of the <hi>RUMP,</hi> with the ſound of a laſh, ſo fatal unto themſelves, have influenced this Nation in ſuch manner, that the genius, as ſome, or the ſpirit, as others call it, of the ſame people, who in time of the Court would rather have choſen a Tapſter then a Courtier, now under the name of a Common-wealth, but in the dregs of confuſion, would rather elect a ballad-ſinger then a Commonwealth-man; Nevertheleſs, while the next Parliament is ſummoned, as it were in the name of the people, and without regal authority, while the full power and free choiſe of the Government to ſucceed is wholly devolved upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties of the people, the preſent Acts and Votes run in ſtile, and every way elſe unto a Common-wealth, nay pitch and ſettle, (to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110096:3"/>the beſt of my underſtanding) upon no other principles or founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then ſuch, whence no other ſuperſtructures or frame of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, (without violence) can ariſe but that of an equal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth or perfect democracy, for what clearer teſtimony of this can be afforded by Art or nature then is expreſſed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent act for the Militia? By this Act you have the Earl of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,</hi> where he weighes moſt, joyned with <hi>Iohn Hudſon</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq.</abbr> and ſome thirty more of the Commons of that County, the like reſpectively for ſome forty more Earls, Viſcounts and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, holding fat leſs proportion unto the Commons with whom they are indifferently joyned, without any advantage in Vote or otherwiſe. Nor, ſhould a man add the whole Peerage of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the whole Comminalty, were it to be doubted but they would hold yet leſs: Sir, all the reſt is but ſuperſtructure, how it is at the root (though perhaps unſeen) is unavoydably felt. The ſword is in the people, and not (without moving propriety) to be wrenched out of their hands. Whereas the people were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently arraied by the Nobility, the Nobility (you ſee) are now arraied by the people; whereas a King could not anciently be brought in but by the Lords, now the King (you will confeſs) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be brought in but by the Commons. Let them come with you to the next Parliament that may, let them go whether they can; if Government be not to be preſerved by any other means then the ſame by which it was acquired, the King can no more be ſuſtained, as heretofore by the Lords, but muſt hereafter (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over in alteration of the forme it may coſt) be ſuſtained by the Commons.</p>
            <p>Sir I beſeech you, was this our old Government? or if (through time as well the innovator as devourer of things) it be of it ſelf become a new one, muſt it be ſtill (as in the reignes of learned predeceſſors) an <hi>Vtopia</hi> or <hi>Chymera?</hi> There is much daring of Larks, but Sir I am upon good grounds, I go (you ſee) upon an act of Parliament let them anſwer to this. Are foundations in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> altered or not altered? for ſuch as the Government is in the root or foundation, ſuch of neceſſity muſt it be in the branch or ſuperſtructure. If the ſword in the hand of the Lords made an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocracy, then the ſword in the hands of the Commons muſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110096:3"/>make a Democracy, or there will be more windfals, for where foundations come to be altered or ſtand one way, and ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures are left hanging another way, it can tend to nothing but ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. Hence that which hath fallen, hence that (if not prevented) which is falling upon this Nation. And what prevention: what remedy! If the Militia be not in the Commons, what means this Act? if the Militia be in the Commons what power have the Lords? if the Lords have no power where is the old Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? if the old Government be gone, what remains but coufu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or to introduce a new one?</p>
            <p>To remove unto a new houſe, though from a worſe unto a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is one of the moſt troubleſome, one of the impatient affaires, a buſineſs in which, how neceſſary ſoever, the family to be well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered muſt be as it were totally diſordered. The caſe of a people neceſſitated unto change of government is of like nature. And as the genius or humor of a family may be one thing in it ſelf, and upon this occaſion ſeem another, ſo the humor or genius of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, be it that they were never ſo weary or impatient of the incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable inconveniencies of their laſt houſe or Government, yet upon queſtion of removal unto a new one, they conceive a kind of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrency, they bemoan themſelves as it were of exile from their native ſoil. Thus it ever was, thus it will ever be in like revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wherein to ſet much by the Genious of a people, is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with them unto their own deſtruction. Leave them in a form under which they know whom to quarrel with, or what to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel for, and this ſickly genious, this quarrelſome humor of theirs is incurable, but bring them under a form in which they can never finde whom to quarrel with, nor what to quarrel for, (which or none is the proper work) and this ſickly genius, this quarrelſome humor of theirs is perfectly cured. There is no looking back for a people advanced by ſo apparent ſteps, by ſo many years travail upon ſuch a journey as the people of <hi>England</hi> now are; to think by a calme of popular impatience to be at home again, is as if a man near the <hi>Indies,</hi>ſhould think to be in <hi>England</hi> again by a turn upon the toe. The foundation of the old government is ſunk, it is fallen it is fallen, when an houſe is fallen it is not grief, not rage,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110096:4"/>not any obſtinacy in the owner can make him live there as he did, it muſt bee new built.</p>
            <p>Nor is newneſs of Government alone (in which caſe our feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city were certain) ſufficient to make it ſecure or laſting, without ſuch prudence in formation of the ſame, as may exactly ſhape and ſit it unto the ſubject matter. To riſe otherwiſe (as hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly ſeen and felt) unto the greateſt heighth, is but to fall loweſt. With ſuch as are in power and under a neceſſity to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a new form, there is no mean between the greateſt ſecurity and the greateſt danger, the higheſt glory, and the baſeſt infamy.</p>
            <p>This by pollititians hath been pronounced univerſally, but now in <hi>England</hi> is more holding then elſewhere it hath ever been, for whereas other governments which have ſuffered like changes, for example that of <hi>Rome</hi> antiently, and that of la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er times in <hi>Holland,</hi> were ſuch from the very beginning, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more perfect Common-wealths, needed but to remove or change their topſtones, as a King into Conſuls, or a Prince for a Stateholder, in which caſe an oath of abjuration was ſufficient: the ancient Government of <hi>England</hi> being ruined in the very foundation, that is in the Ariſtocracy, requires a renovation or reordering of the whole ſuperſtructures, in which an oath of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration can come but to little, for that whether the King be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored or not reſtored it is equally neceſſary the building be ſuch as may ſtand; and that the building of a Government now in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> be ſuch as may ſtand, engageth unto the greateſt prudence in hitting, or the vaſteſt danger in miſſing. The greateſt prudence in hitting, becauſe not a topſtone, or ſome part is to be altered, but the whole frame to be renewed: the vaſteſt danger in miſſing becauſe to work otherwiſe is to work againſt the only foundation which is now the whole people, and for the intereſt of ſomeparty.</p>
            <p>The parties now in England are three, the Royaliſt, the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biterian, and the Sectary. Nor appears it by what the Sectary hath done, the Presbiterian is doing, or the Royaliſt prepares to do, that there is any thought amongſt them of union or of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but of tyrannizing one over another. If the King there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be reſtored by ſome one of theſe, it amounts, (if unto any Government at all) unto one, as new as any, and cantend nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110096:4"/>unto the ſafety of the King, nor of the people, but muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce, a Royal, a Presbiterian, or a Sectarian Oligarchy: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which ever reigns muſt keep down the other two, by unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral force, in the head of which the King muſt be perpetually expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and if any other then the King be advanced unto the head of any one of theſe parties it muſt be with the greateſt ſcandal, and tend but unto the worſe effect, the vaſter diſcontent, diſunion and danger of the people.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> the ſafety of the people, if ever they attain to it, muſt conſiſt in ſuch a forme of Government, as may appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and effectually take in and hold them and all parties of them united.</p>
            <p>To attain unto ſuch a form in <hi>England,</hi> (the Ariſtocracy being irreparably broken) there is no other way whatſoever but by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction of a well ordered Democracy, to which end, the game would eaſily play it ſelf in any hand, but for the parties that are ſtill ſnatching the cards one out of anothers.</p>
            <p>That the Ariſtocracy is broken the act cited maketh not plain confeſſion, but proof. That it is not to be repaired, as ſome medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, by the reſumption of ſuch eſtates, as ſince the later war have been demoliſhed, is plain in that the war began by the ſword in the hand of the people, and ended accordingly; nor, as others, by the recruting of the decayed Nobility with ſome of the richeſt of the Gentry, in that, all ſuch as hold above two thouſand pound a year in this Nation, are not above three hundred perſons, nor, all that which is holden by theſe three hundred perſons, above one tenth of the whole territory. The other nine parts, and ſo by conſequence the whole, being holden by the Democracy, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment able to hold the whole people united, can be no other then an equal Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>In Democracy or in an equal Common-wealth, a Nobility or a Gentry uſurping the leading, never hold it, and not uſurping the leading, never loſe it. The reaſon whereof, throughout ancient experience is not clearer, then at this preſent amongſt us, where no man can imagine, but the Lords in a diſtinct houſe, muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Commons, and not in a diſtinct houſe, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> otherwiſe preferred then by election of the people muſt lead them, to give
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110096:5"/>any peculiar priviledges, under the name of well affected or the like, unto ſome of the Lords in the Senate, were to allow the like claim unto ſome of the Commons in the popular aſſembly, either of which, infects the Common-wealth with inequality, and a Common-wealth infected with inequality is ſo apt to break out into war or diſcord, that it never failed of this effect, where the people have not been the ſole donors of all Magiſtracies and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours by their votes or elections. Certainly it muſt be confeſſed, that elections regularly and freely made, were as eaſie and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, as confuſedly and partially, and elections regularly and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made, would amount unto an equal Common-wealth. But be it as it will, let the annimoſities now broken looſe, elect into the Parliament, elect into the Militia, of the moſt averſe unto Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy, ſo much the better, it reduceth the whole controverſy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a point; for here it lies, If they can ſo patch up the Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that is, the Lords houſe as to make it ſuſtain the ancient weight, the old Government is recovered, and they have confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Commonwealthſ-men; but, let them fail in this one, whatever elſe they hit, the old Government is irrecoverable, and they have confuted themſelves, in which caſe apparently, there muſt be a new form.</p>
            <p>For the introduction of a new form, it is not ſufficient that Acts or Declarations be excluſive of the old, unleſs they be poſitive of ſome new one thet is practicable, there being no certain way of barring any one form, though ſuch an one as cannot ſtand, but by introduction of another, and ſuch an one as can ſtand. If it have been ſaid that a Common-wealth is a Government without a King or Lords, it implies two abſurdities; firſt, that our ancient Government under a King, well ballanced by his Lords, the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertors and vindicators of ancient Liberty, was no Common-wealth, and ſecondly, that our later Governments conſiſting of ſome two or three hundred of the Commons ſitting as long, and doing whatſoever they pleaſed was a Common-wealth, whereas in truth the former Government was much more a Common-wealth (though an unequal one) then the latter. From theſe two abſurdities have ariſen two like effects, one the miſtaken ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of the people, which under the name of a Monarchy, driveth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110096:5"/>at a Common-wealth; the other the deſtruction of that form, which under the name of a Common-wealth, being no form of a Common-wealth, nor indeed of a Government, durſt take upon it ſelf ſuch weight, as now in <hi>England</hi> is in no wiſe to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported but by the beſt form of Government even the full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect form of an equal Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>To the introducing of the full and perfect form of an equal Common-wealth in <hi>England,</hi> there goes no more, but, without other qualifications then ſuch as have been anciently in uſe, to call a free Parliament in the form of an equal Common-wealth. For, <hi>(Formis dat eſſe, dat operari)</hi> the form gives the being and the natural or neceſſary operation or working to every thing.</p>
            <p>To the calling of a free Parliament in form of an equal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, there goeth no more of charge, or trouble, then, that the territory, (to the end the Common-wealth may find no rubs in her bowling or rotation) be firſt more equally divided.</p>
            <p>The territory once equally divided, and the people in every di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, electing annually, equally and freely, two aſſemblies, or (more particularly) into each houſe of Parliament one third part of the Members for three years to act there, (as they muſt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will or no) according to the nature of their form, they by this means perpetuate, not one aſſembly in the ſame men, the certain end whereof is, dividing and ſubdividing, till it come to nothing, but, two aſſemblies, changeable in the perſons, and duly qualified for the whole matter of Government, as not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of any party, but of the wiſdome and intereſt of the whole Nation, and caſt not themſelves upon truſt in men, nor upon the faction incident to a ſingle aſſembly, but, upon the ſtrongeſt ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in nature, even that whence the operation of each creature pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, and which the operation of no creature can exceed, I mean, of form, of ſuch form as transformeth the genius of a people, and rightly ordered, is that onely which in a popular State can, and of neceſſity muſt hold all parties united.</p>
            <p>It muſt be confeſſed how unſeaſonably ſoever, that Common-wealthſ-men, ſuch I mean as are principled, cannot be with the forwardeſt, where it is arbitrary, to adviſe that in ſuch a form as this, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be any Prince or ſingle perſon: nevertheleſs it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110096:6"/>neither hath been nor can be denyed by them, but a like form may (<hi>regno laconico</hi> or <hi>veneto</hi>) admit of a King with royal digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and revenue: Which kind of reign (like that of <hi>Evander</hi> in <hi>Livy, magis authoritate quam imperio</hi>) is that which the ancients (particularly <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) call Heroick, and oppoſe to the Eaſtern, which they call barbarous. And indeed if you obſerve the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and pleadings that are now in mens mouths for our old Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, they run all upon this that the power of the Kings in that was no more. All which practiſe and pleadings are therefore the Stronger arguments againſt the old Government, in that ſuch being the intention of it, the form was not ſufficient to ſecure that intention, witneſs the many bloody wars made formerly by the Nobility, and of later times by the Commons, for nothing elſe but to hold Kings to the true intention of that form; nor is this (were there no other) leſs then good and ſufficient reaſon, to change that form which never made good the true intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Government, for ſuch a Government, as muſt at all points ſecure unto us for the future the true and full intention of that form: And to hold the King in fruition of his royal dignity and revenue, from invading the rights and liberties of the people.</p>
            <p>Of the royal dignity there is nothing imbezeld; and for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue. Putting the caſe that the publike debts amount to three Millions, if the exciſe and cuſtome amount annually to one, this with the <hi>Regalia</hi> yet remaining, might in a matter of twelve years pay off the publike debts, maintaining the Court in due ſplendor, and raiſe a royall revenue in new lands. Whereas reſumption of the old, they being for the greater part in the hands of Souldiers, and in themſelves but ſmall, would be obſtructive and not effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
            <p>It is not inſinuation but an apparent truth, that the King thus reſtored would have theſe not conveniencies, but felicities. He would have the whole honour of the Common-wealth without any of the burthen. He would bring in his party, otherwiſe in danger to be loft out, and by equal participation of ſuch a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment repair them. He would have his hands fairly rid for him of the Scotch Presbytery, a Fanaticiſme neither conſiſtent with a Monarchy nor with a Common-wealth, the baſeſt kind of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110096:6"/>a Pedantiſme, which they who preſs moſt to have impoſed, by the rod, or by power, are leſt able to defend by reaſon. He would look down upon other Kings, as being armed with, or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed (without <hi>Hyperbole</hi>) by the moſt potent Militia in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome both at land and Sea. Had Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> or King <hi>Iames</hi> been founder of the like Government in <hi>England,</hi> how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle had the Crown loſt? How much had the people ſaved in blood and Treaſure? Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> who it is known had good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, ſurceſed courting of her Lords, for God bleſs you my good people: it is true ſince that, different courſes with what ſucceſs I leave to your judgement, have been taken. But other means of Empire than what have been ſhewn, were they definable, are not now attainable in the preſent ſtate of <hi>England,</hi> where, a King henceforth either can have no power at all, or muſt have ſuch power as cannot be limited; for all the waies whereby any King can have any power are but two, either a potent Nobility, or a ſtanding Army. Where a King is founded upon a Nobility, they are the limits of his power, but where he is founded upon an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my his power can have no limit. Where the Nobility then are gone wholly to decay, there is no limiting the power, by which a King ſhall reign, ſeeing it is without a ſtanding Army impoſſible to give him any ſuch power whereby a King may reign.</p>
            <p>But <hi>England</hi> ſeemeth to have a reach, I cannot ſay beyond, but beſide all ages and all Nations. Whether ſhe have an Army or no Army, ſhe is ſtill running upon an invention of her own. <hi>A Parliament with a Council in the intervals,</hi> this if ſhe have no King muſt be the Government, this if ſhe have a King, unleſs he get an Army: and this Parliament muſt have both the debate and the reſult too, that is, be a ſingle Counſel without any check at all and ſo be a Government and no Government, but a tumult as the faction or humor hits, ſometimes popular, ſometimes Oligarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, ſomtimes a <hi>Divan.</hi> For all the kindes of Government that have been or can be are but three. That is a Counſel with a monarch for the check, in which the Counſel debates as the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> after the Common-wealth, or the Turkiſh <hi>Divan,</hi> and a Monarch reſolves as the Roman Emperour, or the great Turk. Or a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel with an Ariſtocracy for the check; in which the people debate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110096:7"/>as anciently in the houſe of Commons and the Lords reſolve, or are ſuch without which there can be no reſult, as the ancient houſe of Peers, in which caſe the Peers will have a King, and this comes to the Government of King Lords and Commons. Or a councel with a Democracy ſo the check as the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> in time of the Common-wealth, debating and the aſſembly of the people reſolving, which the Senate o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> popular aſſembly being rightly ordered, amounts unto an equal Common-wealth. Nor are theſe cheeks ſuch as may be arbitrary, but to be holding muſt each of them ſufficiently preponderate in riches or territory, that is the King, in the abſolute Monarchy, the Lords in the mixed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and the people in the equal Common-wealth, muſt hold the perfect overballance in wealth or freehold; but if theſe be all the kinds of Government that are in Art or Nature, then a ſingle aſſembly as I ſaid before, can be none at all; which were it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to be doubted is ſufficiently acknowledged by it ſelf; In that, a ſingle aſſembly debating and reſolving ſayleth not to fall immediately into faction, and in factions the ſtronger party kick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the weaker, .divides and ſubdivides till the whole come to nothing, as we have had ſufficient experience in <hi>England,</hi> where ſuch an aſſembly having a King, will be thinking to mend it ſelf by pulling him down, and having no King, by ſetting one up. Nor can I conceive which way this in our caſe ſhould be curable, but as hath been ſhewn already, that is, by aſſembling a free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the true form of an equal Common-wealth. An equal Common-wealth is the moſt certain root of the moſt prudent and righteous Laws, becauſe in this form no law can be paſſed but by the wiſdome of the nation, and the true teſt of the publike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
            <p>An equal Common-wealth is the mother of the moſt potent and leſt chargeable Militia, becauſe in this form the whole body of the people is one diſciplin'd Army, taking equally and metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically their turns, as there ſhall be occaſion upon the Guard or in Arms.</p>
            <p>An equal Common-wealth is of all other the moſt proper ſoyle for the plantation and preſervation of true Religion. For wheras the cauſes of corruption in matter of Religion are but two, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110096:7"/>in a Clergy vying for rule with the ſtate, or ignorance. In this form all hope of propagating any by intereſt of their own, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely cut off from a Clergy, in regard that no Clergy without a co-ercive power in matters of Religion, can betake themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any ſuch deſigne: now civil and ſpiritual liberty being inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or imperfect, it follows that for the maintenance of civil li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty (without which this Government is none) an equal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth muſt alſo aſſert and maintain the liberty of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which wholly fruſtrates a Clergy of co-ercive power in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Religion, and yet defends Religion from the other corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or that which might redownd from ignorance, by a known rule and exerciſe of the ſame, or by the prudent inſtitution of a National religion.</p>
            <p>National Religion as to the form, is arbitrary, and therefore in different Countries, or different times, according as a people ſhall grow up in light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or increaſe in knowledge of divine truth, may be different. But in <hi>England</hi> through the education of the people, and as their judgement now ſtands, ought, in my mind, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of the Articles of the Church, and the Common Prayer Book <hi>mutatis mutandis.</hi> For if education amount unto matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and liberty of conſcience be (as the Sectaries now feel) not to be ſecured unto our ſelves, but by giving it unto others, this is that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of worſhip, which the Sectaries (their liberty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſafe) had as leif as any, and the people rather. Nay, whereof the people of <hi>England</hi> are not to be debarred, without conceiving themſelves to be under a force, and reſolving to revenge it as ſoon as they are able.</p>
            <p>In ſume of all, and for a fuller anſwer to your main query, whether a Common-wealth taking in all other intereſts may not be brought to take in that alſo of the King? I ſay whether the King be reſtored or not reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the form of Government in <hi>England</hi> muſt be new and democratical, which that it be alſo rightly ordered is of great concernment: for there is no firme State of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110096:8"/>peace or ſecurity, ſave onely under a proper form of Government. Abſence or imperfection of form produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth a State of War, or of tumult. Whence apparently to reſtore the King upon ſecurity of the form, is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the ſafety of the King and the people, but to reſtore him upon any other conditions then ſecurity in the form, is to caſt both the ſafety of the King and of the people upon the faith of men, nay upon the faith of men, in matters, wherein men cannot keep that faith, and ſo a crime againſt God and man, expoſing a Nation unto ruine.</p>
            <p>Sir, you are obeyed, I have given you my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the point propoſed, in order unto the Feaſt for which you prepare. Never tell me that I obſerve not the manner of your invitation, or that thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings which I aſſert to be from the neceſſity of things, are therein excuſed upon the neceſſity of the times, it moves not me that I reckon without your Hoſt, ſeeing by his means, you and your Fellow-Members go up reſolved to eat Veniſon, where you will find nothing but Beeve.</p>
            <p>But I am (like the Monky) at Cheſts with my Maſters, if you make any further uſe of this Paper, I beſeech you to lay a cuſhion upon my head, by tearing out the name of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your humble Servant</signed>
               <date>April 6th. 1660.</date>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110096:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
